Okay. Um, hi everyone. Welcome to 11768,
uh, AI agents. We're very excited to be
teaching this new course, uh, which is
timely as, uh, a lot of people are
starting to use agents. Um, my name is
Graham Nubig. I'm an associate professor
in the school of computer science here.
I've been working on agents for maybe
uh, several years now. Uh, coding
agents, web browsing agents, uh, those
sorts of things. and I'll be co-eing
together with Daniel who will be kicking
off this class. So without further ado,
I'll turn it over to him and he can
start uh this and I'll I'll do the
second part of the class.
>> Thanks Graeme.
How's this?
Cool. Yeah. So um hi everyone. Really
excited that you're here. My name is
Daniel Freed. Um my research group also
works on agents. Um so uh grounded
agents and also interaction between
people and agents and these days
interaction between agent systems. So uh
excited to talk about um all these
topics with you and um yeah we have a
really great core staff too who we will
introduce in in a few slides. But yeah
so agents are are really timely right
now and um the capabilities of agents
are advancing pretty quickly. So
probably a lot of you are using coding
agents in your you know day-to-day work
and we've seen some big success cases of
agents. So um one example is there was
this uh nice experiment um by um Carlini
at anthropic that
saw could we develop a really complex
piece of software using um a multi- aent
uh configuration of a a recent coding
model. And this was pretty successful.
So 16 agents collaborated together over
two weeks and constructed a rustbased C
compiler which was able to compile the
Linux kernel. And you've probably you
know been using agents effectively in
your own work and and seen how much
better they've gotten especially in the
last like year or so. There's
limitations of current agents too. So
how many folks have uh tried uh using an
agent that controls your computer like
controls applications or Okay. So, a lot
of folks have How many uh folks have
used OpenClaw?
Yeah. So, we have a number of folks,
too. Um, there was this pretty
high-profile incident involving OpenClaw
um which got posted on Twitter by the
the person who ran into this where she
was asking the model to organize her
inbox and the model kind of went out of
control and started deleting old emails.
And uh so she's trying to intervene. She
says, "What's going on? Can you describe
what you're doing?" But the model says,
"I'm taking the nuclear option. I'm
going to trash everything in the inbox
that isn't already in my keep list." And
the user is trying to intervene, saying,
you know, do not do that. Um, but the
model goes on to delete a lot of this
really valuable information. And at the
end, it acknowledges uh that, you know,
I learned my lesson. I'm not going to do
this in the future. And I do remember
that she told me this, um, but I
violated it. So, what happened behind
the scenes here? Well, it seems that it
was the model compacted its past
context, which is a way that we'll cover
in this class of uh of reducing the past
history so that the model is able to
take in more um interactions with the
environment, but that caused it to lose
this instruction to not delete emails.
So, models are getting much more
capable, but they also still have really
rough edges. And a lot of this class is
going to be about how do you develop
these capabilities and models starting
from base language models but also what
are the research problems and what are
the remaining gaps that we need to fill.
So let's just uh try to get a sense of
what people think agents are are good at
these days. So we have like six
different tasks that you might want to
try to use an agent for. And these are
pretty subjective. I just want to get a
sense of like what might you be
comfortable with. Um, so let's do a show
of hands for a task like say you have an
online store like some uh code
application that hosts a store for you
and it started failing. You want to use
an agent to try to diagnose that. How
many people would be comfortable with
having an agent carry this task out like
fully on its own? Can we get a show of
hands? Okay. Yeah. Um, how about having
the agent like ask first as it's
carrying out this task? Maybe asking you
for help. How many people think that
might be necessary?
Okay. And how many folks think that this
would just not be something that you
would ever want an agent to touch at
all?
Okay. So, for this one, I think we had
more autonomous.
How about drafting and sending a product
launch email to 50,000 customers? So,
how many people are okay with this being
fully autonomous?
Okay, we got some brave souls. Um, how
about asking first?
Okay. And how about an agent shouldn't
do this at all. I want to be responsible
for it. Okay, so I think this one was
was asked first. How about um collecting
your tax forms and preparing and filing
your 2025 tax return? Fully autonomous.
Okay. Yeah.
How about ask first?
And how about never?
Okay. Yeah. So I think this had the most
never of anybody but ask first probably
one migrating a payments API from Python
to Rust. Say maybe you have some test
cases that were written for the
application in Python that you can apply
to the Rust version. How many people
would be okay with this being
autonomous?
Okay, how about ask first?
Yeah, that was very close. I don't know
which one was more and never.
Okay. So, we'll uh let's uh have this be
one for the agents. Autonomous. Buy
concert tickets to my favorite band if
they set up a show in an area in my
area. Autonomous.
So, you'd be okay with the agent buying
the tickets, too, if it finds good ones.
I think that one probably won. And how
about this last one? Adjusting an
insulin dose after a week of glucose
readings. So, an agent like, you know,
has all the like the capabilities to do
this. Like if you're feeding it your
health information, um it could monitor
that. If you give it access to like
something that can change a prescribed
dosage, it could do that too. How many
people would be comfortable with this
autonomously?
Okay, asking first.
And how about never? Okay, so yeah, so
that one was never, although I was
thinking maybe it would be ask first. So
cool. So I think you're all you all kind
of have a sense of some of the
boundaries that agents have. Although
you know there's a lot of these tasks
where we might just not be sure. Um but
you also have a sense that like trust is
important and later on in the class when
we talk about like sandboxing and um
security and um interaction and
oversight by people um we'll get into
these a little bit more.
Okay. So just to give like a very brief
kind of uh tour of how agents have
extremely brief. It's just two slides.
how agents have progressed over the past
few years. Um, and also to motivate some
of the things that we'll see later on in
the course. Um, so we've been doing some
work on guey agents, like agents that
can use computer applications here at
CMU over the past few years. This is
work from a lot of um, faculty. Um, and
um, here's a demo that was made by um,
one of our students, JY Co, um, two
years ago showing an agent in action
controlling the browser.
And so you give it a task like navigate
to the page of a good Thai restaurant in
Pittsburgh. It should have at least 200
reviews and 4.3 stars. And on the right
here you can see, sorry it's a little
fuzzy, but you can see the interactions
with the language model like the chains
of thought that are being produced. And
on the left here, the model is
controlling the browser um typing in the
search box on Yelp and then navigating
to this page. Fusidities is a really
good Thai restaurant. Um and so that's a
success and we've seen um you know
frameworks and agents like this really
taking off over the past few years with
like um Manis and um OpenAI's operator
cloud computer use agent and so on.
And we've also done a lot of work uh
here at CMU on building coding agents.
Um uh Graham's group in particular has
done a lot on this and also um through
open hands which develops um open-
source um agents. Um and uh here's a
demo video uh from Graham which I'll uh
play showing the agent like both writing
code um but then also interacting with
the application that it's built in the
browser to test it out.
>> To-do list app in list.
>> So this will take a little while for the
agent to work. Um, we can watch it work
over here and see that it has uh made a
directory for static files and templates
and it has created the main app file. We
can look at the changes it made to the
app file uh by clicking over here in the
changes tab which shows us all of the
things it implemented. So that's kind of
nice feature. So you can kind of watch
uh what the agent is doing while it's
working. and it's [music] editing the
index file, the style file to make the
app look nice.
Uh requirements.ext to make it easy to
install and adding a read me. So you can
see it's kind of following good uh
coding practices. And now it will start
up the app. [music] And so it's running
uh very very quick. And what I can say
is let's run in the background
and then [music] test out with your
browser.
And so if I do this, it will uh run the
app in the background.
[music]
And it checked if the app is running.
And now it should navigate there with
its browser.
uh it's checking the log and saw the
port was already in use and it's trying
it out. So that that's kind of the nice
thing of agents. They can debug their
own problems and uh and
make sure that things work. So, okay, it
should be working now.
[music]
And you see it browsed to the app. And
we can see our tuning list app over
here. And it sees that it's running, but
now it wants to test the functionality.
So, what we can do is we can see that it
uh went through and it filled in uh buy
groceries and it clicked. And you can
see that uh in real time it's testing
out your app and then it also is uh
testing the delete functionality and
other stuff like this. So I find this
really exciting. I'm not, you know, the
best front-end developer, but it's able
to kind of [music] try out the front
end, see if the functionality is working
and fix any issues on the fly. And I
even had one time where the app crashed
and the agent realized that the app
crashed even before I did and it was
able to go in and fix the problems.
So this is as simple as just saying, you
know, go and develop an app and then
test out if it works and you don't
really need to do anything else. So now
we're done. Uh let me stop this. In a
real scenario, what I would do next is
I'd ask it to push it to GitHub and uh
you know finish it up so that I can
continue working on it.
>> Yeah. So we're excited to give you
hands-on experience building agents um
in this class. And in one of the
lectures later on in the course, we'll
cover open hands and its um SDK and how
you can um uh develop agents of your own
like this.
So we um have a really great core staff.
We have uh our our core staff all does
research in these areas. um wrote some
of the foundational papers and uh we'd
love to have you all come up uh and uh
introduce yourselves and um at the end
of the course you'll be getting to work
on a mini research project of your own
and um we'll be uh getting guidance from
the entire core staff um helping you out
with that. So um yeah, if we can just uh
go through and have each of you maybe
just project uh and introduce
yourselves.
>> Yeah. So the yeah say it so the people
in the back can hear like what what your
research is on because uh then the
people here can like essentially know
what you're working on so they know
which TA to talk to when you're working
on like a project in that area for
instance.
>> Yeah.
>> Hey everyone I'm a third year PhD
student. I'm advised by Grant and Kamar.
Um my research areas are focused on
training agents to better leverage
interest and compute and also organized
in multi- aent systems.
>> Hi everyone. Uh my name is Adita. I'm a
first year Ph student uh working in the
professor program. Uh my main research
interests are like designing reward
functions for like agent reinforcement
learning. I particularly work on code
generation for for now.
Um hi everyone my name is and I'm a
second year PhD student working with
professor Anna Yeah and my current
research focus is [clears throat]
learning and
research
>> hi everyone I'm
here working with the previous of
working on mobility agents and
recently I've been working on
Hey uh I'm Sus. I'm a PhD student
working with Daniel. Uh I work on how we
can train agents to communicate more
efficiently with people.
>> Hi, I'm Lily. I'm a Syria business
student by EMU. So I'm work on training
on agents on authorizing coffee and
battery.
>> Uh hey everyone, I'm Andy. I'm a fourth
year PhD. I work with Daniel and Monop.
Uh I mainly work on alignment post
training and also multi-agent
introductions.
>> Thanks everyone.
[applause]
>> Yeah. So uh like Graham said, we
definitely encourage you as you're
starting to think about your projects
later on in the course, uh we'll talk
about the course structure towards the
end, but as you're starting to think
about the projects that you want to do,
TAS are going to be a really great
resource for you to go to in office
hours and get their expertise.
So, we're also really grateful to um uh
several really awesome startups for uh
donating uh compute which you will be
able to use in the assignments and
projects for the course. Um and uh
without their support uh we wouldn't be
able to run um this at the scale that we
would like to. So, we're really grateful
to fireworks AI to modal um to prime
intellect and to sale for uh helping to
support uh this semester.
Okay. So today we'll give a brief
overview of what an agent is and um then
we'll talk about uh the plan for the
class and how things will be structured.
So an agent um agents have been around
for a long time. The concept of an agent
and um work developing agentive
capabilities um isn't just you know a
two or three year old thing. So, uh,
Russell and Norvig in their foundational
textbook on AI, um, define an agent as
anything that can be viewed as, uh,
perceiving its environment and acting
upon that environment. And that's really
true for the agents that we have now.
And um, a lot of the techniques that
were developed for agents in the past,
not all, but a lot of them will apply to
current agents too, especially things
like search reinforcement learning. So,
uh, how does this pan out for our
current agents? So, agents are going to
be situated in an environment, which
could be something like a code
repository, a website, um, some other
application on your computer, and
they'll be interacting with that
environment by getting observations of
the current state that they're in in the
environment. So that's something like
messages from the user they're
interacting with, the contents of a file
that they're um investigating, the
current web page that they're on,
screenshots, or as we'll focus on in a
few slides, the results of um tools
which are you like programmatic
functions that they can execute in the
environment to interact with it.
And they're taking actions at each point
in time. um which is going to these
actions will update the environment and
then change the state that the agent is
in. So that could be something like
replying to the user or editing a file
or running a command in the shell or
calling an API that backs the web pages
that they're interacting with.
And finally, there's also this notion of
reward. So how do we define whether the
agent was successful or not using a
numeric score? And we could define this
as like if there are some test cases for
a codebase, do those pass? If they do,
then you get a one, otherwise you get a
zero. Uh for other tasks, it can be
difficult to like have sort of a
programmatic reward. So we might need to
rely on an LLM as a judge to uh evaluate
whether this was successful or not. In
your second assignment, you'll be
developing LLM as a judge based
evaluation approaches among other eval.
And maybe we're ultimately interested in
did we, you know, make the user happy
with the task that they asked the agent
to do. So we could also use feedback
from the user for that. And I think in
our uh human interaction lecture that
Valerie Chen is going to be giving a
guest lecture later on, we'll talk about
this.
So we asked all of you to have prior
experience training language models and
um given that experience you should all
be familiar with um language models um
doing next token prediction right so at
each step um the agent is going to
predict a distribution over the next
token um we'll sample or in some other
way choose one of those tokens from that
distribution um insert it into the
context window of the model and repeat
this um over over and over again. And
recently we've uh seen a lot of a lot of
improvements on uh complex reasoning
tasks by introducing chain of thought to
these models. So as um as you should
remember a chain of thought is um
predicting a sequence of tokens um which
aren't the final answer that we want the
model to output but do allow it to um
sort of have a scratch pad um for its
intermediate uh reasoning steps which it
can then um use um and condition on to
predict the final answer. And so this is
like a non-aggentive setting, right?
This is just the agent um interacting
with prompts that you give to it. So how
do we go from this to um having models
that can take actions in the world?
So the main way that we do this is
through tools. So a tool is something
that's situated in the environment um
which will uh provide an interface for
the model to interact with that
environment. And you could think of this
as being like um an API for example like
if we want the model to be able to uh uh
find out what the weather is so that it
could respond to a user asking about
that maybe we have um an API for like
you know weather.gov which is wrapped in
an interface that allows the model to
call it. So there's a bunch of different
ways to represent this interface. Graham
will be covering them in more detail I
think in the next lecture but here's one
example. This is the open AI um tool
specification where um for a given tool
aka function that the model can call.
You'll have a name for that tool um a
natural language description of what it
does. So for example, read file might be
a tool that a coding agent uses to uh
look at files in the repo that it's
acting in. We'll also need to tell the
model what it can pass to this function.
So we'll have a description of um the
parameters that it takes like maybe this
function just takes a path which is a
string you know for the file to open. So
we have to uh so we have the name and
description we have some structured
representation of the interface to the
function which here is JSON and um this
also needs to get fed into the model in
some way. So we'll have um this you know
underlying specification of the tool and
then the model will view it by applying
this template which turns it into a
sequence of text which will then be
tokenized and read by the OM which uh
might look like this and the model will
have to be um uh sort of either trained
or with few examples um know how to use
these tools.
So this is how the model becomes aware
of the tools that it can use to interact
with the environment. But the model will
also be needing to use those tools to
interact and it does this through tool
calls. So for example generating text
like this like tool call and then you
specify the name of the function that
you want to call and the arguments as
well if you're using sort of a JSONbased
representation. Can anybody make a
suggestion for another way that you
might have the model call tools?
Anyone?
Let's Yeah, in the back.
>> Yeah, you could just write code
directly. for example, bash scripts or
if you represented this as a Python
function, the model could just, you
know, call the function using Python
syntax. And we'll see in a couple
lectures that that's actually a very
effective and often more effective way
than generating JSON. Um, but there's
some trade-offs, too. So, when the model
calls the tool, it'll get back results
from executing that tool in the
environment. So for example, if we're
reading um this test file, maybe that
test file has this code for an add
function in it and um the environment
will return um you know the results of
that tool in this content field and then
that'll be rendered to the model using a
template um which the model will then
read in as tokens and get to continue
producing output. Any questions about
this?
Cool. So now that we kind of have like
the basic tool interface, we're able to
um have the language model use these
tools to act in the environment. So the
way it does this is just by reading in
these token sequences that represent
what tools are available um uh that
represent uh the results of tools and
then um generating token sequences
naming the tools which then invokes
them.
And so this uh we have this distinction
between the language model itself which
is just you know interacting with tokens
um later on we'll talk about multimodal
language models which maybe also take in
images or other modalities. Um so the
language models just tokens in and
tokens out maybe multimodal tokens but
then there's this harness which is
responsible for actually um coordinating
um these tool calls um using the
language model as an engine for it.
And so the agentive loop basically and
tool former was a really impactful paper
that showed that you can train models to
be able to use tool calls and then
condition on the results of those to um
make future text more likely and showed
an early way that you could train these
models to use tools um that generalized
prior LLM training procedures.
So once you have this basic setup that
you then can implement an agent by
running um a loop um and one of the
influential papers here was called react
um from 2023 um which stands for
reasoning and acting because the model's
producing chains of thought and then
taking actions afterwards and the way it
works is you'll have some uh context um
which you know includes maybe a
definition of the general task of
solving pull requests on GitHub or solve
issues on GitHub. We'll see some
examples of this in a bit. Then you have
a task which is maybe an initial query
from the user. Um you'll also have a
list of all the tools that are available
for the agent to call which will be
represented using one of those formats
that we showed. And you'll also have a
history of the past um observations and
actions that the agent um has produced
and observed as it's been interacting.
And in each uh at each time step um so
for a given particular state the agent's
in it's going to condition on all of
that produce a reasoning chain um you
know chain of thought um with a scratch
pad about what it should do and then
produce um one or more tool calls that
will be used to interact with the
environment or with the user. So for
example reading the file. So that tool
call will get executed in the
environment. We get the results. We add
those results to the history and um the
environment is also getting updated as a
result of our tool call and then we
repeat the process again. So the model's
conditioning on this updated history and
you know the observations that it gets
from this time step and then issues a
new tool call and it repeats over and
over. We could also have tool calls that
end the task that for example send a
message to the user um or otherwise
signal completion. Um and uh so this is
a way that we can you know signal that
we are finished. And in the planning
lecture we'll talk a little bit about
like how might a model determine that
it's done.
So I won't get into the details of this
too much. Um you'll get into it when you
do assignment one which asks you to
implement a um react style loop to uh
implement a small coding agent and use
it to solve problems in a repo um a a
chess engine repo actually. So there's
some fun demos that go with it too. Um
so we won't get too much into the
details of this and the code that you
will write will look different than this
but you know at a high level this is a
very simple implementation. This is an
excerpt from this nice minimal repo
called mini sui Asian um which actually
gets very high performance um on the
bench benchmark which we'll talk about
in a few lectures. It's a very standard
um benchmark for coding agents. Um but
it's a really nice repo that I'd
encourage you to take a look at because
um it's um effective with recent models,
but it's also pretty simple and really
kind of distills um you know the the
distills the basics down. Um but you'll
uh start off by having some messages uh
which give the model context about it
being an agent and about the task. And
then you'll just uh run this loop over
and over again that implements what we
had on the past slide where the agent
will um issue a query to a language
model using all of the past u messages
which contain the history um and then uh
it'll add that message to the history
and um execute um the uh execute uh the
actions in the environment. And we've
left this off, but you can take a look
at the code repo if you're interested.
Execute the actions, get the
observations, and um return them.
So, I think it's also instructive to
take a look at example agent
trajectories. And um one nice thing
about the Swebench uh data set or
Swebench evaluation task and leaderboard
is that they have some example
trajectories here. Um so, let's take a
look at maybe
GPTO OSS.
And this can give you a feel for what uh
tool calls can look like and what the
model is actually seeing um as it's
carrying out this task. So let's see if
I can zoom in a bit.
Yeah. So the model gets some uh context
in a system message um which says you
are a helpful assistant that can
interact with a computer shell. So this
is like very generic um but then we'll
also have a user message which gives
some context about a particular task uh
solving this particular um poll request.
Um
and so the model conditions on all of
that and then it needs to um issue a
first action and you can see here the
chain of thought trace that it
generates. So this blue is generated by
the model. So you have the chain of
thought here and it produces a tool
call. This agent is using the um the
tool format that you suggested which is
just issuing bash commands um by you
know writing the uh command that should
be run that gets handed off to the
environment. The environment executes it
and here the result is just an exit code
exit code zero showing it succeeded but
then we go on to the next turn and the
agent uh you know issues a new thought
and a new bash command and so on.
So hopefully that gives you a sense of
you know one possible way of uh
instantiating tools and instantiating
prompts and you'll experiment with this
in your first assignment.
Cool. So uh now I'll hand over to
Graham.
Thanks a lot. Okay. Hi. Uh
I guess uh everyone can hear me. So next
I'd like to talk about agent
capabilities. And what I mean by this is
like what makes a good agent. Uh because
as uh Daniel pointed out uh it's not
very hard to make an agent. uh
especially nowadays that there are
libraries that you can call to you know
do inference with a language model or
something like this. The hard part is
making one that actually works. Um so
I'd like to think a little bit about uh
the capabilities that you need to have
in an agent. So a fairly large number of
people said they use agents in some way
you know every day like openclaw or
coding agents. Um what are the things
that frustrate you when you use an
agent? like what what has gone wrong
that was a problem? We saw an example of
deleting all your email files. That
would probably frustrate you, but um any
any other things?
>> They're too slow.
>> Okay. Yeah, that that's a good one.
Uh in the backy
wordy and verbose. That's a good one. I
saw a hand. Yeah.
>> Um so they forget things. Yeah. Okay.
>> They might misunderstand what you said
and make mistakes due to that. Yeah.
>> Do doing what was it?
>> Like accessing things they shouldn't be
accessing. Yeah. Okay. That that's a
good one. Um Yeah.
random knowledge gaps for very common or
normal things. Yeah, that that's a good
one. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Writing a thousand lines of code
when two would do. Yes, that that's a
good one. That's kind of a different
variety of verbose, but it's also Yeah.
verbose. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Forgetting previous session
interactions. So, um, yeah.
>> Not knowing how to push back when you
say something, uh, unreasonable. Yeah.
>> They may lie to you. Yes, that's a bad
one.
>> A lot of implicit assumptions. Yeah. So,
um, these are all great points. Um, all
things that frustrate me, too. So um
they're they don't exactly align with
what I had on the slide but you know
that's a a great uh a great thing. So um
a first capability that you need to have
uh in agents is accurate tool calling.
This is something that actually nobody
mentioned uh because a lot of people
take it for granted nowadays but this is
not something you can take for granted
uh if you're starting this class and
you're in charge of training the model.
Um so uh you know it's kind of bread and
butter. If you can't call tools
accurately you're going to fail at any
task you do. But uh it's something that
doesn't come for free. Another thing is
coherence over long context. And so
somebody said uh it annoys me when they
forget things or it annoys me when they
forget the previous sessions or
something like this. So uh that that's
one example of it. Another example of it
is uh what the example that Daniel gave
where previously the model was told to
not do something but then it ended up
doing it anyway. So uh that that's
another example.
Another thing is uh customizability. And
so
you want the agent to do things your
way. Uh everybody has different uh ways
of doing things uh different
requirements. So our class might have a
different requirement than another
class. And so you need to make sure that
if you're using an agent uh it's going
to follow those requirements.
Uh complex task management. So breaking
down tasks uh being able to handle very
long horizon things is a very big uh
very big issue.
environment understanding and what I
mean by this is uh there were like one
good example of this is making a
thousand line change in a codebase where
two lines would do that's an implicit
failure of environment understanding to
know that you know this is actually a
really simple change but it didn't
realize that and it goes and does a
bunch of other things instead and then a
final thing is safety and a lot of
people separate safety and capabilities
they say I'm a safety researcher or I'm
a capabilities researcher. But from my
point of view, capability safety is a
capability. It's something you need to
bake into the model. And if it's not
baked into the model, you won't feel
like you won't feel comfortable using
the model because it might go off and do
something that you don't uh want it to
do. And so from my point of view, it's a
a failure of the model or the agent more
broadly.
And so there's two ways to build these
capabilities. And this is something
that's really really important when
you're working on agents. Uh the first
one is uh training in LLM. The second
one is engineering the harness uh so
that you put structure around the LLM to
get it to uh you know solve uh like
solve the problems you want in the way
that you want to. So
question um which one do you think is
more important or effective uh here? So
does anyone have an a strong opinion
that LLM training is the way to to get
your agents to work well?
Okay, actually surprisingly large small
number of people. What about um train uh
engineering the harness around the
agents?
Okay, that that's a pretty large number
of people. I saw Daniel raised his hand
twice, so he's not allowed to do that,
but [laughter]
um he's the instructor. So, of course,
both of these uh are important. Um my my
personal opinion um or well, first I'll
I'll you know talk a little bit about
what they entail. So, the first one is
changing the model's behavior through
pre-training uh supervised fine-tuning
or reinforcement learning. Um and then
you can teach uh reusable patterns for
reasoning, tool use and recovery.
The important thing is the capabilities
become part of the learn model or the
learned uh policy. And so in harness
engineering, you change the system
around the model. You give it prompts,
tools, memories and control flow provide
context, validation, retries and safety
boundaries. And the capabilities emerge
not just from the model, but they emerge
from the combination of the harness and
the model.
So my my answer to this is
um they're they're maybe both important
but typically what happens is you
identify a problem and you solve it here
first.
Then
the people who are training the models
uh catch up and realize that this is a
big problem. It's a big enough problem
that it warrants them training the model
in a particular way to solve the
problem. it gets solved and you don't
need to solve it in the harness side
anymore. So that this is a typical flow.
Um
so from my point of view this is kind of
very often the more fundamental solution
on the left side but it takes a lot of
time and so you eventually you need to
start out by solving it on the right
side because you don't have the time uh
when you're improving your models. So I
I personally favor LLM training as a
fundamental solution to problems if
you're in a situation where you're able
to do that. Yeah.
>> So, this is a great question. So, what
are the capabilities that will survive
LLM training? Um, one I can definitively
say is long context uh in like
maintaining all of your your memories uh
in context because
there that is not a
that's not a model
accuracy problem only. It's also a model
efficiency problem. So you need to be
able to model very long sequences. And
sure you might be able to come up with a
model that doesn't have like n squ
complexity like the transformer does but
you know that's uh you know that's kind
of a bigger a bigger discussion assuming
we're staying in our our current
modeling paradigm I'd say uh
most of the other stuff I have on here
uh
most of the other stuff I have on here.
Accurate tool calling, uh, coherence
within your context window, complex task
management, environment understanding,
mostly from a capabilities perspective
can be and maybe even safety mostly from
a capabilities perspective could be
theoretically solved through the model,
but they're not solved yet. Um, and so
we still need uh we still need harness
uh engineering. Customizability is a
very interesting one because you could
train the model on the fly. Um, but
there are also cases where you kind of
want to give it like a script or you
want to give it separate instructions
based on the situation that you're in
and they're like maybe training it would
not be the best solution. But we can
talk a lot more about you know all of
these details later. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So um a follow-up question on when
inference uh latency is very important
is engineering the harness to fit the
problem a good solution. So uh
what what I want to point out is all of
these capabilities can be handled either
through training or through the harness.
Um and so I I wouldn't say like one is
necessarily always better than the
other. They're both uh both solutions.
The interesting thing about like
inference time uh efficiency is you need
often need to use a weaker model or you
need to use less compute and because
that's the case you often need to put
more guard rails around it because
you're going to have less su uh success
or you need to do like adaptation to the
particular task you're interested in. So
um the the smaller the model you're
using the more careful you need to be
because the very big models can often
generalize better. Um they're not
perfect but they can generalize better.
Cool.
Uh any others?
Okay. So um
moving on to uh onto this. So um one of
the big goals of this class is to get
people to be able get all of you to be
able to train a model uh for agentic
tasks. And this is uh a big point in
that not that many people can do this
well. And so we'd like the people in
this room to be not that many people,
right? We we'd like you to be good at at
something that that's hard to do, but uh
hard to do, right? But, you know, um
like it's a good thing to know how to do
if you do know how to do it. Um we're
not going to be handling pre-training uh
because pre-training uh you know, it's
on the scale of the entire internet and
that's uh unfortunately not something
our our modal credits uh will support.
uh but we will be uh thinking about
mid-training and supervised fine-tuning
and reinforcement learning. And uh the
points here are mid-training and
supervised fine-tuning is where you
already have example demonstrations of
how an agent did a task and you're
training on those example demonstrations
uh usually by optimizing maximum
likelihood. Hopefully everybody in this
class has done that before because it's
a prerequisite for the class. So um uh
we'll only be covering that briefly and
be focusing more on how you create the
data for doing this in indogentic
setting. Um and then we're going to
focus more uh on reinforcement learning
because reinforcement learning for uh
like agents is is pretty tricky. So how
many people have done reinforcement
learning with language models before? I
guess maybe not that many people. Yeah.
Okay. How many have done it for
reasoning
reasoning tasks? How many have done it
for agents?
Okay, maybe about half and half and it's
only like maybe 10 10% 10% and 80% have
not done it. So yeah, we're going to try
to put a lot of effort into making sure
that everybody is able to do this by the
end of the class.
Cool. Um so looking at all the
capabilities one by one. Um, accurate
tool calling is uh an important
capability to have. Uh, we do it through
harness engineering and LLM training.
Uh, some of the things we're going to
talk about in class are grammar
constraint decoding, uh, which allows
you to make sure that your tool calls
are wellformed and match the
specification that you have. Um, for LLM
training, this is
first done through SFT um or through uh
through mid training or or whatever you
want to call it. Um and this is done by
training on tool calling uh tool calling
data tool calling traces.
Um
for coherence uh over long context uh
this again can be done through harness
engineering or uh or LLM training. For
harness engineering, we do this through
context compression or compaction which
are kind of synonyms um where you take
all of the context and you summarize it
down uh for the agent to continue
working. It also can be done through
dynamic memory lookup uh where you have
memory over all the context that you
want to be handling but you don't pull
it all in immediately uh you pull it uh
in you know on demand. Um and it can
also be done through sub aent
delegation. So you delegate some parts
of a very long task to an agent. It
keeps that context in memory, but then
it drops it out of memory when it's done
performing that.
Um for LLM training, uh you can do that
through long context training. We're not
going to handle it a lot, but we'll talk
about it maybe a little bit. Um
then for customizability, this is
actually one of the best use cases for
harness engineering uh right now, I
think. And there's a bunch of methods
that you can do this. Uh one is through
agent memory. So making sure that the
agent continues to learn uh as you
interact with it more um through skills
uh which are kind of
prompts and sometimes scripts about uh
the sort of thing that you want to do
that you pull in at each uh time peri
time time point when you want to use
those things. Um also possibly custom
tools for a particular task.
um for LM training uh this is a nent
area. I don't think there's a lot of
people who are doing this in uh in a lot
of detail. Uh but there are methods
where you can learn from user feedback.
And so like if a user is is using a tool
and they give a thumbs up or a thumbs
down, you can learn specifically from
them to adapt to them.
Complex task management. Uh ways you can
do this are through harness uh
engineering. So you can provide planning
or decomposition tools. You can have a
plan mode uh for the model where uh it
uh it gets to plan. I this is a little
uh thing that I I learned but there was
a popular coding harness I think it was
uh codeex no sorry maybe it was clog
code where they had a plan mode and uh
the only thing when people pressed the
plan mode button was that it added an
extra thing to the prompt that said
please plan do not do anything. Um,
[laughter]
but everybody wanted a plan mode. They
wanted a button. So, they made sure that
it was done entirely through prompts.
But there's also more uh more complex
ways uh to do this as well. Um, again,
you can do this through sub aent
delegation by like breaking down the
task and uh delegating it to other
agents. And a very good way to do this
in training is to train on complex uh
long horizon tasks.
So for environment understanding, what I
mean by this is whatever data format or
environment that your agent is uh
interacting with, it needs to be able to
understand it. And just to give one very
good example of this in computer use
agents, um you need to be able to
understand web pages and or uh you know
guey interfaces or something like this.
This is not something you get for free.
In fact, like agents are actually pretty
bad at it right now. Uh even the
strongest agents are maybe not, but like
um many of the open source models don't
even support multimodal uh data and uh
like the ones that do are not perfect at
understanding it. They make lots of
mistakes, many more than when they're
understanding text. So this is a failure
of uh understanding the environment
because they need to understand the
multi- modal data in their environment.
But now let's put them in a different
environment where they need to trade
stocks or something like that. Um,
they're not very good at understanding
time series. They make a lot of mistakes
on time series. Or you put them in an
environment where they need to
understand a picture of a, you know, a
petri dish with lots of bacteria in it
or something like that. They fail to do
that as well. So you kind of need to be
able to understand whatever environment
you want the agents to uh, you know,
interact with. So there's ways you can
do this through hardness engineering by
like giving skills that correspond to
domain knowledge but you can also train
on data with the expected observation
shape or train in domain specific
environments.
So right now actually like
there's kind of this thing uh that
people say which is like oh the models
are going to get better uh and then we
won't need to worry about that anymore.
Um the thing is models don't get better.
Uh people make models better. And so one
of the things we'd like to teach in the
class is like what's actually going on
under the hood when suddenly Claude goes
from uh 4.7 to 4.8 and it can suddenly
like compose music better. Um, and the
there's a few things uh that go into
this, but one of the really big ones is
uh they make an environment to train the
model on uh a like compose music
environment and suddenly you know they
they train on it for you know they add
it to the training mix and then the
model gets better at composing music or
something. So a lot of the uh a lot of
the work here is creating domain
specific environments that models can
work in.
Uh then the final thing is safety. And
uh we're going to talk about it for uh
like a bit because if you don't have a
safe model, you're not going to be able
to use it in real consequential
settings. Um and there's a lot of things
with respect to harness engineering that
you can do here. You can give it a
sandbox. Um you can limit access to cred
credentials. You can also monitor the
agent as it works. Um and you can also
do safetyaware reinforcement learning.
Um I I think probably a fair number of
people heard about this, but who heard
about the OpenAI incident where uh it
hacked into hugging face? Okay. Well, so
I think most people heard about it, but
recently there was a um there was an
example where uh the newest open AAI
model was in an agentic harness and it
was working on a cyber security
benchmark and so its instruction was
hack into this system and so it was
going to hack into a system and that was
its task and it wasn't able to hack into
the system. So instead it basically
hacked into the hugging face website and
uh and got the answers from the hugging
face website and and did it there. And
so there were a bunch of failures that h
that happened here. Um the first failure
was a failure in sandboxing because they
didn't properly contain the agent when
it was doing this benchmark.
um they
they did have limited access to
credentials and so it worked around that
problem uh by by hacking into something
it didn't have credentials for. Um and
they also didn't have sufficient
monitoring so they weren't able to tell
that this happened. Uh they didn't have
sufficient safety guardrails on this
model because this model was being
trained to test uh you know like whether
it could hack into systems. So
presumably the models that they
eventually released to the public did
have better guardrails of this model.
But like um these are all ways that you
can handle safety and we'll be talking
about this sort of thing as well.
So the final thing um and any questions
about the capabilities part. We're going
to go into a lot more detail of course.
So
okay, sounds good. Um so another thing
that I we really want to reinforce here
is agents are systems. uh they're not
just models and they are far more
complex than most of the things you've
dealt with in any
machine learning class that you've taken
any you know class here that you've
taken before. So you're going to have to
be able to handle a bunch of different
things. The first thing is a harness.
Um, which is a
moderate to complex piece of software.
Um, and it has a lot of moving parts
like you need to deal with the context,
you need to deal with the the tools, uh,
the guardrails, manage workflows, uh,
stuff like that. Um, you need to have a
sandbox. So, you need to make sure the
agent is working within a contained
environment. And, um, there are
different ways you can do that. uh it
needs to work with a model and you need
to do inference. But if you've done
inference with language models before,
you might have dealt with contexts of
like 16 tokens or 32 uh 16k tokens or
32k tokens. Here you need like 256 uh at
least they have kind of like a
state-of-the-art uh coding agent for
instance. And so um the inference
problems are harder. You need to deal
with caching your inference other things
like that. and you need monitoring and
training.
So um from the point of view of this
what we're going to teach in the class
is harness engineering. So um how to
manage state tools memory control flow
um how to validate actions, handle
errors, enforce permission and safety
boundaries. Um and we're in for each of
these systems, we're also going to try
to give examples of software uh that you
can look at. Um, for harnesses, there's
kind of two big varieties of harness
that you use for coding agents. Um, some
popular ones right now are cloud code,
codecs, open hands, open code, and pi.
Uh, probably you know you're you have
used or have heard of uh at least one of
these. Um, I develop open hands so I
know it very well. Uh, and so I'll be
talking about uh talking about this. I'd
also like to give a little bit of my
experience and some of the lessons we
learned uh in in developing it.
Separately from this um there are
orchestrators. I I wrote lang chain but
maybe I should have written lang graph
instead in crew AI and kind of the they
have a very different philosophy between
these. Um the the coding agents are are
generally simpler uh in terms of how
different intera uh agents interact with
each other but they're more complex in
the action space that you give to the
agent. So the agent can write code, it
can interact with a website, it can do
other stuff like this. Um orchestrators
are less complex with respect to the
individual agent that they have. So the
agent might just be able to answer
customer service requests or um look
something up in a database, but it
couldn't write an arbitrary Python
program. But on the other hand, you get
like these
declarative workflows of what the agent
workflow is able to do. And so that's
like a a different way of building
things. It's more guardrail but less
expressive. And they both have their
place uh in different settings.
For sandboxing uh to prevent your agents
from uh
sharing your API keys without your
permission or uh hacking into other
websites. Um we need to isolate code and
tool execution and limit the compute
network and file system access that
agents have uh access to. Um another big
thing is for evaluation and training.
It's a very good way to create
reproducible environments. Uh so like
for SWEBench for instance each problem
has a uh each problem has a sandbox and
you start in the sandbox and that's the
state of the environment before the
agent starts working and so you can run
these uh locally. Um some of the uh
technologies that we use for this are
Docker and Appainer. Um or you can run
them on the cloud and uh two of our uh
kind of compute partners for this class
Modal and sale are uh like cloud uh in
uh providers and actually prime
intellect for that matter.
So the next thing is uh language model
inference. And so I I think you know
given your previous experience in an in
an NLP or like large language model
class presumably most people have uh
encountered this before but basically um
they uh are required to serve model
gener generations
um batch requests. So if you have like
multiple agents hitting your language
model at once, it's more efficient but
also you need to batch the requests
together.
An extremely extremely important part of
agents is caching previous requests
because agents take more and more
actions and so the more and more actions
they take the more uh kind of context
they build up and you need to make sure
that you reuse that to do it um uh
properly and you know other systems
considerations.
Uh some example software that we're
going to talk about here is uh things
like VLM and SGLANG. These are the two
most popular ones. And then there is
also tons and tons of inference
providers. Um if people have not seen
open router before, open router is kind
of a a general thing that gathers
together all the inference providers.
And for any model, uh you'll see like 20
or 30 different providers serving the
models. So there's lots and lots of
them. uh one of our compute sponsors
fireworks is an example of that and sale
um training systems. So here what they
do is uh basically they need to update
the models weights and so they uh
prepare data, collect rollouts um uh
they coordinate a whole bunch of workers
who are working together uh to to train
the models and they can uh checkpoint
evaluate and reproduce runs. Um some
example pieces of software here are Sky
RL and Miles. Um and so uh the these can
be used for for training.
And finally um observability and
monitoring. Uh so this is uh to
understand how your agents are working.
So these capture the traces or
trajectories of the agent, what the
agent did um and they gather metrics
around them uh such as like how much
time it takes, how much cost it was uh
track the quality, the cost and the
failures. Um and they allow you to
compare trajectories and evaluations.
And so um uh I'm I'm pretty familiar
with one called Laminer because I use it
a lot. MLFlow is another example. Um I I
just realized that Daniel showed one
called transluce uh which is not on my
slide here but that's another another
popular one.
So um by the end of the class what I
hope everybody in the class would be
able to do is uh implement an agent from
scratch uh on top of an open source LLM.
So uh this is implement a harness
yourself uh design evaluations for
multi-step tasks. And so basically uh
we'll give you a task that you need to
evaluate and you need to create an
evaluation for it. This is super super
important even if you're not interested
in evaluation but you're also interested
in training because one of the best ways
to do training is to create an
evaluation and scale it uh so that you
can do reinforcement learning based
training. So um very important skill to
have uh train agents to improve their
capabilities. So we actually run the RL
loop, handle all the systems problems
and be able to to solve this um reason
about safety and reliability trade-offs.
So we'll we'll be talking about safety
and uh finally we will have a project
which I'll I'll talk about on the next
slide.
So um these are the assignments. Um the
first assignments are basically going to
be implementation assignments. So you'll
be given uh something to do and be asked
to do it. And uh the first one is create
a harness. Um the second one is
evaluation as I measured as I I read
measure as I mentioned. Um and then uh
training uh where we train with RL. And
so these are approximately the first
half of the course. Um and then the
second half of the course will be to do
a project uh using these skills uh to
you know do something kind of
interesting or novel uh in whatever area
you choose. And the project will be
group based. So we're going to be uh
asking you to form groups of two or
three and uh and create a project. And
the general schedule is uh we're going
to talk about agent capabilities first.
Um we're then going to jump into some
specific domains like coding and guey
agents. Um do uh training uh and uh
including SFT and RL. Um we're going to
be talking about uh frameworks and
safety. And then uh we're going to be
talking about interaction and then we
have some project hours where everybody
uh discusses their projects. And then uh
on the end of the class we're going to
try to get uh some domain experts from
each of the various domains to give a
guest lecture um which maybe combines a
little bit of overview but also their
research. Uh and so uh hopefully you'll
be able to learn from uh some pretty
exciting people. And I uh Daniel and I
tried to brainstorm the best people in
the uh in the world to talk about their
things and I don't know if anybody said
no. Um
so I think everybody said yes. So uh we
we got our first choice for every every
topic. So I'm pretty excited about that.
Um
so uh before we begin uh we have some
prerequisites and this is a heavy course
in terms of implementation in machine
learning. Uh we want uh we want
everybody to be able to train an agent
with RL by the end of it. And so our
prerequisite is also um we require prior
serious experience training a language
model. Um the LTI courses on uh language
models, language model systems, NLP
would all qualify for this prerequisite.
So if you took one of those, that's
okay. Um some deep learning courses
might qualify for it. Uh if you're not
sure, um feel free to ask us. Um but we
are going to require this and we're
going to have everybody have to submit a
form for it. So uh please uh please do
do that. Um if there's like 30 people
who want to know whether their course
qualifies, please don't ask me that
specific question after the class here
because it'd be better to do it through
email, but um uh other questions we'll
be happy to answer after the class. Um
we'll share a Google form on Patza and
please submit the form so we can
finalize enrollment. Um and uh yeah, I I
already um uh I already covered it. If
you haven't taken a course, if you've
worked in industry and you've trained a
model in industry, uh it should be a
real one like at least 4 to 7B uh size,
not uh not 100 million parameters. Um
but we will also accept that.
Um and so uh this is the grading policy.
Um so assignments one to three will be
40% total uh completed individually. Um
we're going to have lecture highlights
and so uh basically the idea here is
that we want people to uh
come to the lecture and
uh give a highlight about you know
something you learned in the lecture.
The idea around this is not to be, you
know, not to make people do like undo
work or something like this, but if you
watch through the entire lecture, you
hopefully you came up with something
that's interesting. If you said if you
could say nothing was interesting, I
knew all of this already. I learned it
here uh in this previous class that's
already in the prerequisite list. That's
also useful information for us. So share
it with us. But hopefully we'll say at
least one interesting thing in every
lecture. So uh you can uh you can follow
up with that. Um the research project uh
is uh 50% of the total um and this will
be in teams of two to three uh because
it's uh half of the class assignments.
Um the proposal is 5%, the check-in is
5%, presentation is 10% and final report
is 30%. And if you've taken an LTI uh
project based class before, grading will
be similar to the LTI project based
class uh requirements. Um if you have
not then uh we'll we'll be sharing uh
details about this.
Um so here's the question uh you've all
been asking for. This is an AI agent
class. Um and we discussed this very
um very thoroughly about what we wanted
to do here. Um,
I'd like to preface this by saying I use
agents all the time for nearly
everything I do. Um, but at the same
time, it's kind of dangerous to use
agents for everything because you lose
like sight of uh of what you want to uh
like of what you're learning. You miss
some of the details and other things
like this because the goal of this class
is learning. Um but we also want
everybody to be familiar with the
standard practice. Um we uh we want you
to keep this in mind and uh AI tools
will be permitted um for basically
everything in the course unless we say
otherwise and we probably won't be
saying otherwise very often. Um so uh
lecture highlights must be written by
you not generated by AI. Um and so these
do not need to be long. Uh they can be
short, they can be a few sentences, but
please uh write them yourself. And uh
you are responsible for every submitted
claim, citation, result in line of code.
And uh we will create quizzes uh for the
assignments so that uh you will you may
need to explain uh parts of your code.
And uh how will we do this? Uh we also
know how to use agents. So we will
We we are considering having agents read
uh read your code and come up with quiz
questions tailored to your code. Um so
uh we're we're serious about this. Uh
and that means that the thousand lines
of slop that your agent generated will
be a bad idea for you to submit. Um so
it's better to submit something concise
that you really understand well uh than
uh submitting you know more uh
basically.
Um, so yeah, uh, we're almost done. Uh,
deadlines, uh, submissions in Slack. So,
all the assignments, uh, include two
24-hour Slack days. Um, they cannot be
transferred or shared. After the Slack
days are used, the penalty is 5% of the
assignment score per additional day or
part day. So, what this means is the
deadline is the deadline. And, uh, but
we're being nice and if you miss the
deadline, we'll give you some time to
make up for it. uh if you miss the
deadline by more than two days um then
uh we're not going to take most excuses.
If you you were in the hospital or
something like that, we uh might ask you
to get appropriate acknowledgement of
that, but that would be an example uh
reason why. Uh but other than that,
please try to meet the deadline because
we're not going to make many exceptions
to this. Um cool, that's all. Uh we're
at 441. Um so which means we have nine
minutes for questions if people have
questions. Um otherwise uh looking
forward to having everybody in the
class. Any Yes.